Chapter 99.
The deloon air. Now it has been related how Ahab was want to pace his quarter deck,
taking regular turns at either limit, the binnacle and main mast, but in the
multiplicity of other things requiring narration, it has not been added how
that sometimes in these walks, when most plunged in his mood, he was want to
pause in turn at each spot, and stand there strangely eyeing the particular
object before him. When he halted before the binnacle, with his glance fastened
on the pointed needle in the compass, that glance shot like a javelin with the
pointed intensity of his purpose, and when resuming his walk, he again paused
before the main mast, then, as the same riveted glance fastened upon the riveted
gold coin there, he still wore the same aspect of nailed firmness, only dashed
with a certain wild longing, if not hopefulness.
But one morning, turning to pass the deon, he seemed to be newly attracted by
the strange figures and inscriptions stamped on it, as though now for the
first time beginning to interpret for himself in some monomomanic way whatever
significance might lurk in them. And some certain significance lurks in all
things, else all things are little worth, and the round world itself but an
empty cipher, except to sell by the cartload, as they do hills about Boston,
to fill up some morass in the Milky Way.
Now this deloon was of purest virgin gold rad somewhere out of the heart of
gorgeous hills whence east and west over golden sands the headwaters of many a
pactolus flows and though now nailed amidst all the rustiness of iron bolts
and the verdigrees of copper spikes yet untouchable and immaculate to any
foulness it still preserved its keto glow nor though placed amongst a
ruthless crew in every hour passed by ruthless hands, and through the live
long nights shrouded with thick darkness which might cover any pilering approach,
nevertheless every sunrise found the deloon where sunset left at last, for it
was set apart and sanctified to one awkriing end, and however wanting in
their sailor ways, one and all, the mariners revered it as the white whales
talisman. Sometimes they talked it over in the weary watch by night, wondering
whose it was to be at last, and whether he would ever live to spend it.
Now those noble golden coins of South America are as medals of the sun and
tropic token pieces. Here palms, alpacas and volcanoes, sun's discs and stars,
ecliptics, horns of plenty, and rich banners waving are in luxurant profusion
stamped, so that the precious gold seems almost to derive an added preciousness
and enhancing glories by passing through those fancy mints so Spanishly poetic.
It's so chance that the deloon of the Peekquad was a most wealthy example of
these things. On its round border, it bore the letters Republica del Ecuador,
Kito. So this bright coin came from a country planted in the middle of the
world and beneath the great equator and named after it. And it had been cast
midway up the Andes in the unwaning climb that knows no autumn. Zoned by
those letters you saw the likeness of three Andes summits. From one a flame, a
tower on another, on the third a crowing while arching overall was a
segment of the partitioned zodiac. The signs all marked with their usual
cababalistics and the keystone sun entering the equinoxial point at Libra.
Before this equatorial coin, Ahab, not unobserved by others, was now pausing.
There's something ever egotistical in mountain tops and towers, and all other
grand and lofty things. Look here. Three peaks as proud as Lucifer.
The firm tower that is Ahab. The volcano that is Ahab. The courageous, the
undaunted and victorious fowl, that too is Ahab. All are Ahab. And this round
gold is but the image of the rounder globe, which like the magician's glass
to each and every man in turn but mirrors back his own mysterious self.
Great pains, small gains for those who ask the world to solve them. It cannot solve itself.
He thinks now this coined son wears a ruddy face. But see I he enters the sign
of storms, the equinox, and but 6 months before he wheeled out of a former
equinox at Aries. From storm to storm.
So be it then. Born in throws, it is fit
that man should live in pains and die in pangs. So be it then. Here's stout stuff
for woe to work on. So be it then.
No fairy fingers can have pressed the gold, but the devil's claws must have
left their moldings there since yesterday, murmured Starbucks to
himself, leaning against the bull works.
The old man seems to read Belshazar's awful writing. I have never marked the
coin inspectingly. He goes below. Let me read. A dark valley between three mighty
heaven- abiding peaks that almost seem the trinity in some faint earthly symbol.
So in this veil of death, God girds us round. And over all our gloom, the sun
of righteousness still shines a beacon and a hope. If we bend down our eyes,
the dark veil shows her moldy soil. But if we lift them, the bright sun meets
our glance halfway to cheer. Yet oh, the great sun is no fixture. And if at
midnight we would fain snatch some sweet solace from him, we gaze for him in vain.
This coin speaks wisely, mildly, truly, but still sadly to me. I will quit it
less truth shake me falsely.
There now's the old mogul saliloquis stub by the triworks. He's been twigging
it. And there goes Starbucks from the same. And both with faces which I should
say might be somewhere within nine fathoms long. And all from looking at a
piece of gold which did I have it now on Negro Hill or in Corier's Hook. I'd not
look at it very long air spending it.
Humph. In my poor insignificant opinion, I regard this as queer. I have seen
deloons before now in my voyagings. Your deons of old Spain, your deloon of Peru,
your deloon of Chile, your deons of Bolivia, your deons of Papan with plenty of gold materles
and joe's and half joe's and quarter Joe's. What should there then be in this
deloon of the equator that is so killing wonderful by Galconda? Let me read it
once. Hello. Here's signs and wonders truly. That now is what old Baich in his
epitome calls the zodiac and what my almanac below calls ditto. I'll get the
almanac. And as I have heard, devils can be raised with double's arithmetic. I'll
try my hand at raising a meaning out of these queer curb cues here with the
Massachusetts calendar. Here's the book.
Let's see now. Signs and wonders and the sun. He's always among them.
Here they are. Here they go. All alive.
Aries or the ram. Taurus or the bull.
And Jiminy. Here's Jeeminy himself or the twins. Well, the son he wheels among
them. I here on the coin he's just crossing the threshold between two of
the 12 sitting rooms all in a ring. Book you lie there. The fact is you books
must know your places. You do to give us the bare words and facts, but we come in
to supply the thoughts. That's my small experience. So far as the Massachusetts
calendar and Bowic's navigator and Deb's arithmetic go signs and wonders, eh pity
if there is nothing wonderful in signs insignificant in wonders. There is a
clue somewhere. Wait a bit. Histark by Jove. I have it. Look you, Deloon.
Your zodiac here is the life of man in one round chapter. And now I'll read it
off straight out of the book. Come, Almanac. To begin, there's Aries or the
ram. Leerous dog. He begets us. Then Taurus or the bull. He bumps us the
first thing. Then Geminy or the twins, that is virtue and vice. We try to reach
virtue. When low comes Cancer the crab and drags us back. And here going from
virtue, Leo, a roaring lion, lies in the path. He gives a few fierce bites and
sirly dabs with his paw. We escape and hail Virgo the virgin. That's our first
love. We marry and think to be happy for I. When pop comes Libra or the scales,
happiness weighed and found wanting. And while we are very sad about that, Lord,
how we suddenly jump as Scorpio or the scorpion stings us in the rear. We are
curing the wound when wang come the arrows all around. Sagittarius or the
archer is amusing himself as we pluck out the shafts. Stand aside. Here's the
battering ram. Capricornous or the goat.
Full tilt he comes rushing and headlong we are tossed. When Aquarius or the
water bearer pours out his whole deluge and drowns us. And to wind up with
Pisces or the fishes, we sleep.
There's a sermon now written high heaven and the son goes through it every year
and yet comes out of it all alive and hearty. Jolly he aloft their wheels
through toil and trouble. And so alo here does jolly stub. Ah jolly is the
word for I adoon but stop. Here comes little kingpost dodge round the tri
works now and let's hear what he'll have to say. There he's before it. He'll out
with something presently. So So he's beginning.
I see nothing here but a round thing made of gold. And whoever raises a
certain whale, this round thing belongs to him. So what's all this staring been
about? It is worth $16. That's true. And at 2 cents the cigar, that's uh 960
cigars. I won't smoke dirty pipes like Stub, but I like cigars. And here's 960
of them. So here goes Flask a loft to spy him out.
Shall I call that wise or foolish now?
If it be really wise, it has a foolish look to it. Yet if it be really foolish,
then it has a sort of wisish look to it.
But if asked, here comes our old mansman, the old hearse driver he must
have been. That is before he took to the sea. He luffs up before the deloon.
Hello. And goes round the other side of the mast. Why, there's a horseshoe
nailed on that side. And now he's back again. What does that mean? Hark! He's
muttering voice like an old worn out coffee mill. Prick ears and listen.
If the white whale be raised, it must be
in a month and a day when the sun stands in some one of these signs. I've studied
signs and know their marks. They were taught me two score years ago by an old
witch in Copenhagen.
Now, in what sign will the sun then be?
the horseshoe sign. For there it is, right opposite the gold. And what's the
horseshoe sign? The lion is the horseshoe sign. The roaring and devouring lion.
Ship. Old ship. My old head shakes to think of thee.
There's another rendering now, but still one text. All sorts of men in one kind
of world, you see. Dodge again. Here comes Quiqu all tattooing. Looks like
the signs of the Zodiac himself. What says the cannibal? As I live, he's
comparing notes, looking at his thigh bone. Thinks the sun is in the thigh or
in the calf or in the bowels, I suppose, as the old women talk surgeons astronomy
in the back country. And by Jo, he's found something there in the vicinity of
his thigh. I guess it's Sagittarius or the archer. Now he don't know what to
make of the deloon. He takes it for an old button off some king's trousers. But
aside again, here comes that ghost devil Fidala, tail coiled out of sight as
usual, Oak in the toes of his pumps as usual. What does he say with that look
of his? H only makes a sign to the sign
and bows himself. There is a sun on the coin. Fire worshipper depend upon it.
Oh, more and more. This way comes Pip.
Poor boy. Woody had died. Or I He's half horrible to me. He too has been watching
all these interpreters, myself included.
And look, now he comes to read with that unearly idiot face stand away again and
hear him park.
I look, you look, he looks, we look, you look, they look upon my soul. He's been studying
Murray's grammar, improving his mind, poor fellow. But what's that he says
now? Hist. I look, you look, he looks, we look, ye look, they look. Why, he's
getting it by heart. Hist again.
I look, you look, he looks, we look, ye look, they look.
Well, that's funny.
And I, you and he. And we, ye, and they are all bats. And I'm a crow. Especially
when I stand at top of this pine tree here. Caw caw caw caw. Ain't I a crow?
And where's the scarecrow? There he stands, two bones stuck into a pair of
old trousers and two more poked into the sleeves of an old jacket.
Wonder if he means me. Complimentary, poor, lad. I could go and hang myself.
Anyway, for the present, I'll quit Pip's vicinity. I can stand the rest, for they
have plain wits, but he's too crazy witty for my sanity. So, so I leave him muttering.
Here's the ship's naval, the stablo here. And they are all on fire to
unscrew it. But unscrew your navl, and what's the consequence? Then again, if
it stays here, that is ugly, too, for when u nailed to the mast, it's a sign
that things grow desperate. Ha ha, old Ahab, the white whale, he'll nail you.
This is a pine tree.
My father in old Talin County cut down a pine tree once and found a silver ring
grown over in it. Some old darky's wedding ring. How did it get there? And
so they'll say in the resurrection when they come to fish up this old mast and
find a dloon lodged in it with bedded oysters for the shaggy bark. Oh, the
gold, the precious, precious gold. The green miser will hoard you soon. Hish
hish. God goes among the world's blackberrying. Cook ho. Cook and cook
us. Jenny. Hey. Hey. Hey. Hey. Hey.
Jenny. Jenny. And get your ho cake done.